Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the Plain Bagel. Today is the
day that we see the first company cross
the finish line in the AI race to go
public. With Elon Musk's SpaceX, the
company whose prospectus reads like a
science fiction book, complete with the
pictures for easy reading, officially
start trading its shares publicly under
the ticker SPC-X. Breaking records and
making Elon Musk the world's first
trillionaire. And depending on who you
ask, it either signals the start of the
retail investor AI golden age or the
beginning of the end of the AI bubble.
You see, this was just the first of
three massive AI focused IPOs that were
expected to see this year. With
Anthropic, the company behind Claude,
itself having filed confidentially
earlier this year to go public likely
sometime in the fall, and OpenAI, the
company behind ChatGPT, announcing just
this week that it too had filed its S-1
with the SEC. And as mentioned, these
IPOs are breaking a number of records uh
for SpaceX. Beyond just uh the massive
market capitalization, there's also the
fact that the company put aside a record
percentage of its shares to give retail
investors access to its IPO. And with
Anthropic and OpenAI themselves having
previously been valued just shy of $1
trillion each, the three companies
together are set to raise more money by
going public than all other US IPOs
combined since at least 2022, with total
proceeds from IPOs in 2026 expected to
blow previous years out of the water.
All of which is remarkable in its own
right, uh but especially so when you
consider how relatively small and
unprofitable
these companies are. Of the three
companies, Anthropic is the only one on
track to see profitable operations this
year. Uh with SpaceX actually losing
money at the operating level, and these
companies spending well beyond their
revenues investing in scaling out. With
OpenAI set to spend $600 billion is by
2030 on compute spend compared to its
annualized revenues of just 25 billion
dollars. So, it's easy to see why these
companies are scrambling to go public.
They need a heck of a lot of money, and
public markets offers another faucet
through which they can access that
capital. Uh but given how heavily
focused these companies have been in
specifically targeting retail investors
with their IPOs, it's raised some
concerns that these companies will soon
be burning through the pensions and life
savings of everyday investors to fuel
their AI money furnaces well before even
demonstrating a viable business
strategy. With SpaceX specifically
turning a lot of heads with its abnormal
prospectus, which could very well go
down in history as one of the most
bizarre ever seen. Uh with the company
advertising itself as a bet on Mars
colonization, enterprise AI, asteroid
mining, and data centers in space, while
also putting forth the company's mission
as  to build the systems and
technologies necessary to make life
multi- planetary, to understand the true
nature of the universe, and to extend
the light of consciousness to the stars.
Now, I don't know what extending the
light of consciousness to the stars
entails, but I imagine it has to do with
that Joe Rogan episode he was on back in
2018. Regardless, given the concerns of
an AI bubble seemingly pulling public
investors deeper into it, I wanted to
cover the topic to discuss the IPOs and
the details we have, the broader
implications for the market, and things
you yourself should consider if you're
hoping to use one of these companies to
go to the moon,
whether figuratively or literally, since
space tourism is another one of SpaceX's
hypothetical business lines. And the
first half of this video will really be
focused on SpaceX since we have the most
details about that company now that it's
public. Uh but I'll leave chapters in
the description down below if you want
to hop to the different sections of
today's topic. SpaceX, as you might be
aware, was a company started and uh
mostly controlled by Elon Musk that, as
the name implies, is heavily involved in
the space industry, where it's actually
built a decent name for itself. The
company is famous for its rockets,
having pioneered techniques for reusing
rocket boosters, and holding a dominant
position in the space launch industry,
representing 80% of global mass to orbit
since 2023. And its connectivity
business, aka Starlink, where it offers
internet access via satellite
connection, is actually a fast-growing
profit-making business. However, earlier
this year, amid the AI hype, SpaceX
decided that it was going to get in on
the action. With Elon Musk combining it,
or more specifically using SpaceX to
acquire his other company, X AI, known
for the social media platform formerly
known as Twitter, and the AI formerly
known as Mecca Hitler. With the AI
segment making up about 17% of the
company's total revenues, but managing
to take up the majority of the company's
capital expenditures, with it spending
quickly dominating the rest of the
business, which is why the company's
being brought up in this broader
discussion of the AI gold rush. Now,
with this IPO, SpaceX is actually only
selling 4.2% of its company stock,
represented by 555.6
million shares roughly, uh meaning that
most of the company will continue to be
held by the private investors who owned
the business before the IPO. With Elon
Musk himself retaining 42% of the
company's equity before dilution. And at
an IPO price of $135 per share, the
company is set to raise at least $75
billion from the share sale, all of
which makes SpaceX the largest IPO
capital raise on record. Uh with the
company set to exceed its original
market cap objective of around $1.75
trillion, which will actually lead to it
displacing Elon's other business, Tesla,
as the eighth largest US company by
market cap, which is remarkable given
that the company's revenue doesn't even
crack the top 200 list. Uh which brings
us to the first reason why many are
viewing this IPO as absurd. SpaceX
essentially hit the market with a
price-to-sales ratio of over 90 times,
which puts it well above most other
publicly traded tech companies. Uh
Google and Meta, for example, who
themselves have AI businesses and are
actually profitable, trade at
price-to-sales ratios of around that 10
times level. And while these rich
valuations are typically justified by
higher growth rates, historically
anyway, that's not what we've seen.
SpaceX's AI segment isn't even its
fastest growing segment internally, with
the business growing just 12.5%
year-over-year in the latest quarter,
with revenue for the company as a whole
increasing just 15.4%
well below the revenue growth rate seen
by its competitors. However, most of
SpaceX's valuation is very clearly being
tied to its future potential, rather
than how the business stands today. Uh
in fact, Morningstar analysts have
argued that based on current
performance, SpaceX is worth less than
half of what it's IPOing for. So, it's
really what Elon Musk has planned for
the business that has investors excited.
But that brings us to another absurd
aspect of this IPO, uh where the company
lays out the road map for its future.
The firm's prospectus. Uh you see, when
companies IPO, they submit what's called
an S-1 form, in the US anyway, to the
SEC for review. A document that contains
all the necessary disclosures and
information, so that investors can make
an informed decision when they buy into
a company. And in conventional Elon Musk
fashion, the SpaceX prospectus has been
pretty unconventional. Right off the
bat, investors have to scroll through 11
pages of pictures of rocket ships and
other space tech before they even get to
the table of contents, which I suppose
is fitting since it's quite common for
people to throw in a bunch of random
rocket ships when they're trying to pump
something. Now, not long after this,
we're faced with a quote from Elon Musk
philosophizing about being a spacefaring
civilization, and of course the
company's Star Trek-esque mission
statement. Now, in addition to a number
of these grandiose statements being made
throughout the document, the prospectus
also includes a number of moonshot
business ideas.
Literally, uh because most of them
involve carrying out operations in space
for
some reason, including traveling around
Earth via spaceship, space tourism,
in-orbit manufacturing, traveling to
Mars and setting up businesses there,
building in-orbit data centers, and
developing human augmentation systems. A
good chunk of which, by the prospectus's
own admission, is science fiction, since
the technology for many of these things
is either unproven or nonexistent. Now,
with all of SpaceX's focus on space,
you'd be forgiven for forgetting that
SpaceX is an AI business. But to
convince the non-believers, the
prospectus includes an outline of the
business's total addressable market,
essentially what it sees as its future
revenue potential. With 93% of this
amount being derived entirely from its
artificial intelligence opportunities,
namely enterprise applications. Now,
beyond those mistaken for thinking we're
talking about a rocket company here,
these figures might surprise a number of
people. Uh for one, the total
addressable market is about the size of
the entire US economy. And regarding
enterprise applications, most view Grok
as a mere extension of the X social
media platform. In fact, even
internally, the company actually
combines many of its operating figures
for both the X social media platform and
Grok, seemingly demonstrating that its
use is primarily for social media. And I
don't know that many enterprises are
keen on integrating an AI model known
for undressing people on X into their
workflows. Uh the one business case the
company did put forward in its marketing
material of Grok being used for an
enterprise effectively chalked up to
being a glorified Google Translate,
which doesn't really demonstrate this
massive potential. And the idea of Grok
as being a contender with Anthropic and
OpenAI regarding this sort of enterprise
application hasn't really been helped by
the recent announcements from the
company that it would be renting out
compute power to Anthropic for 1.25
billion dollars a month and Google for
920 million dollars a month. Because
while these deals might prove lucrative
if they follow through, uh given that
they alone would actually double
SpaceX's revenue from 2025, it's a bit
confusing from a company that's claiming
Grok's going to dominate the space when
it's renting out its capacity to other
AI models that are more known for those
enterprise applications. So, you can see
why the SpaceX IPO has raised so many
eyebrows. Beyond just the sheer scale of
it, the way the company's being marketed
is just entirely different from the
company investors are
actually buying into here. And that's
without getting into the other quirks
that come with this. Uh the fact that
Elon will be retaining 85% of the voting
rights over SpaceX thanks to having a
special share class that has 10 times
the voting rights of class A shares. A
good chunk of the proceeds from the IPO
simply going towards paying off existing
obligations despite the company
marketing that it will go towards
developing its business. The story that
Musk actually required companies working
on his IPO to subscribe to Grok. And as
mentioned, the company being heavily
focused on garnering retail investment.
With SpaceX opting to reserve up to 30%
of its shares for individual investors
compared to the typical 5 to 10%. And
the company even launching a retail side
website, spacexipo.com,
where it provided investor access to the
company's prospectus, roadshow
presentation typically reserved for
institutional investors, and a fact
sheet, and listed out all the brokerages
where individual investors could go and
access IPO shares. So, in the context of
the great AI IPO race, this one really
takes the cake in a number of ways.
Now, regarding the two other IPOs here
with Anthropic and OpenAI specifically,
we don't yet have that many details on
these companies' operations. While a
number of details around revenue and the
like has been leaked by private sources,
the companies have filed their
prospectuses confidentially, meaning the
SEC is reviewing it privately before
it's released to the public. But, what
we do know is that with recent private
funding rounds, Anthropic has been
valued at 965 billion dollars and is set
to hit 10.9 billion dollars in revenue
during the second quarter, which could
actually set the company up for its
first operationally profitable quarter.
And OpenAI has recently been valued for
852 billion dollars, with management for
OpenAI similarly highlighting a desire
to reserve a sizable portion of their
shares for retail investors. And the
thing is, these aren't even the only
companies going public here. While they
certainly are the largest and most
notable, given that OpenAI and Anthropic
have been sort of competing head-to-head
to be the largest pure-play AI business,
we've already had a number of companies
in the ecosystem like CoreWeave and
Cerebras go public recently, and
companies like Anduril, Cohere, and
Databricks themselves eyeing IPOs in the
near term. And even among currently
public companies, we have businesses
issuing shares. Google's parent
Alphabet, for example, recently
announced plans to sell 8 billion
dollars' worth, on par with SpaceX's own
capital raise to help fund its AI
ambitions, with Meta itself considering
a similar move. So, you can see that a
lot of companies are rushing to raise
money from investors to help fuel their
intensive spending to build out their AI
infrastructure, either for their own use
or for their customers, and compete for
that dominance in the industry. Which
has led to some raising concerns that
these IPOs represent a way for private
investors to exit and cash out right at
the top of the hype. That we're
democratizing access to these companies
right before the bubble pops. With
SpaceX, for example, given that the
public float is going to represent less
than 5% of the entire company, there are
concerns that the stock could experience
meaningful selling activity from
insiders as their staggered lockup
periods expire. With nearly $1 billion
of shares set to unlock within the next
couple of months alone. And given a
number of actions from key players
leading up to this IPO, it seems
increasingly likely that individual
investors will end up as the exit
liquidity for some of these insiders.
Beyond SpaceX itself focusing on giving
access to the retail base, we've also
seen brokerages like Fidelity, for
example, actually lower its capital
requirement from $500,000
to just $2,000 to give smaller investors
more access to this IPO. With it being
quite typical for IPOs to only be
accessible by larger investors. There's
also been the story around index
companies like Nasdaq and the FTSE
Russell, which each eased their criteria
for index inclusion allegedly at the
request of Elon Musk himself to
effectively fast track SpaceX's
inclusion into some of their flagship
groups. Something that could see SpaceX
join indices like the Nasdaq 100 within
its first 15 days, which is
unprecedented and something that would
lead to automatic buying of the stock
from funds and investors who passively
follow these indices. Meaning regardless
of how people feel about the AI bubble
or SpaceX, they could start seeing it
included in their 401k or pensions. Now,
the optimistic framing of this is that
democratization piece, right? Giving
individual investors unprecedented
access to what is seen as a
technologically innovative company on
its IPO. And in Elon's case, it does
seem like a smart move to bolster his
company's valuation. He has a massive
social media following that in part
includes a bunch of retail investors,
and he's known for his
unconventional approach to public
relations, which combined with the
company's grandiose aspirations makes it
a good contender for meme stock status,
which we all know from our corporate
finance 101 class is a tried and true
strategy for capital raises. But the
pessimistic view, of course, is that
this introduces a lot of risk to
everyday retail investors at times
whether they want it or not. Elon Musk
is, of course, no stranger to
controversy and has a history of things
like self-dealing even with SpaceX
itself. Something that's not helped by
his retention of majority control, and
the man doesn't have the best track
record on following through with his
promises. In fact, we recently had a
piece from The New York Times analyze
Elon Musk's success rate on his
ambitious goals, which found that of the
602 objectives set over the past couple
of decades, only 19% were actually
achieved with 35% being late or failing
to deliver, 13% being outstanding, and a
third just being too vague or difficult
to assess. A high retail concentration
also makes the stock more susceptible to
price volatility, something admitted by
SpaceX itself in its prospectus. And
that could eventually impact future
capital raises for the company. It's
actually why a lot of companies that are
pursuing high-growth innovative
industries and are unprofitable often
remain private to avoid the regulatory
burden and the public investor scrutiny.
The sheer size of these IPOs has also
raised concerns about the crowding out
of investments in other areas and even
within the tech scene itself. One of the
reasons many are describing this IPO
mania as a race to go public is because
each subsequent company to release and
then debut its shares is likely to face
a smaller and smaller pool of available
or even interested in investor capital.
Truth is, there's only so much money to
go around. Some have even speculated
that the sell-off in Bitcoin represents
investors selling their ownership to
raise capital for these investment
opportunities. But it's questionable
whether there's enough investor appetite
or dollars available to allow all these
companies to meet their objectives,
especially when we're seeing Treasury
yields floating closer to that 5% level.
If that figure rises higher, it could
discourage stock market investing and
valuations. It's why many people are
watching the SpaceX IPO so closely. As
the largest IPO on record, it's going to
help set the mood for the other
companies going public later this year.
Finally, there are the grander concerns
about this all being part of a bubble.
The S&P 500 already sits at a
price-to-earnings ratio of around 31
times and has become increasingly
concentrated among tech companies. Uh,
with the top 10 stocks, the majority of
which are somehow involved in the AI
ecosystem, representing nearly 40% of
the entire index. So, any correction
could be far-reaching in terms of its
impact on the market and investors as a
whole. And while the S&P so far hasn't
changed its criteria to allow these
companies to enter the S&P 500, their
hypothetical inclusion would only make
this concentration worse. And with these
companies having such rich valuations,
it leaves very little margin for error
if AI doesn't live up to its full
potential. Goldman Sachs, for example,
one of the investment banks behind the
SpaceX IPO, has argued that SpaceX could
see its AI revenue grow by 100 times
over in the next four years,
demonstrating some pretty exuberant
expectations for technology that, while
certainly promising, hasn't yet
demonstrated that long-term business
sustainability. One survey by McKinsey
released in November found that 88% of
respondents already use AI in at least
one business function with nearly 31%
scaling their use. But so far, just 39%
report an impact on enterprise earnings
before interest and tax from their AI
use. So while AI use certainly seems set
to grow, it's questionable whether rates
will continue at their current
blistering pace, especially with 30% of
survey respondents having experienced
inaccuracies at least once with their
models. And all that adoption is with AI
companies taking a loss on their
operations. Eventually, they'll have to
charge a sustainable
price for their offerings. We're already
seeing a number of companies move
towards a token consumption pricing
model that basically charges users based
on how intensive their request is. And
it's yet to be seen whether AI adoption
will justify these higher prices in the
long term. Now, the flip side to all
this is that this is a technological
revolution. These models are rapidly
improving. The companies are already
seeing meaningful revenue growth. And
all of this justifies the hype and the
valuation, which is certainly possible.
The issue with technological revolutions
is that they're pretty hard to track or
predict. But with these companies,
again, being priced for perfection, a
lot of that upside is being priced in,
which leaves investors with a lot of
risk. So it's up to you whether you
decide to invest in SpaceX or Anthropic
or OpenAI. Certainly, if the near-term
revenue growth these companies have seen
continues into the future, they could
prove quite attractive. And there's no
denying the impressive technological
feats these companies have achieved and
could potentially achieve in the future.
And with SpaceX specifically, some
people like the Elon factor, from his
political takes to his truck designs.
His company Tesla has managed to retain
a rich valuation in spite of falling
earnings and slowing revenue growth. And
some are optimistic that with grand
objectives like the joint venture
Terrafab, where the company plans to
make a massive semiconductor factory,
and grander objectives of going to Mars,
that Musk will somehow find a way to not
only make these ideas work, but also
make a bunch of money in the process.
But, it's hard not to be skeptical
around how profitable these companies
might end up being, especially when you
talk about the goals that some have set
for themselves. So, as innovative as
these companies have been, there's also
no denying that they present
meaningfully higher risk than your
typical mega cap stock. And just like
Musk's predictions that we would have a
1 million robot taxi fleet by 2020, and
that SpaceX would reach Mars by worst
case scenario this year or by 2031, it's
worth taking these visionary promises
with a grain of salt
when you're the one funding them.
Anyway, that's the video. Thanks for
joining me today. I hope you find it
helpful. If you did, please do make sure
to like, subscribe, all that good stuff.
It does help the channel tremendously.
And let me know your thoughts on the
SpaceX IPO or uh the general AI IPO
race. Uh thanks again for joining, and
as always,
be safe out there.